three chapter 46 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna suul Part four chapter 46 Jake and the Lady
I was sold to a corn dealer and baker, whom Jerry knew, and with him he thought
I should have good food and fair work. In the first he was quite right, and if my
master had always been on the premises I do not think I should have been
overloaded, but there was a foreman who was always hurrying and driving everyone
and frequently when I had quite a full load he would order something else to be taken
on. My carter, whose name was Jakes, often said it was more than I ought to take,
but but the other always overruled him it was no use going twice when once
would do, and he chose to get business forward Jake like the other carters,
always had the check reain up, which prevented me from drawing easily, and by
the time I had been there 3 or 4 months
I found the work telling very much on my strength. One day I was loaded more than
usual, and part of the road was a steep uphill. I used all my strength, but I
could not get on, and was obliged continually to stop. This did not please
my driver, and he laid his whip on badly.
“Get on, you lazy fellow,” he said, “or I'll make you.” Again I started the heavy load, and
struggled on a few yards; again the whip came down, and again I struggled forward.
The pain of that great cart whip was sharp, but my mind was hurt quite as much
as my poor sides. To be punished and abused when I was doing my very best
with was so hard it took the heart out of
me. A third time he was flogging me cruy when a lady stepped quickly up to him,
and said in a sweet, earnest voice: “Oh!
pray do not whip your good horse anymore I'm sure he is doing all he can, and the
road is very steep I'm sure he is doing his best.” “If doing his best won't get this
load up he must do something more than his best; that's all I know, ma'am,” said
Jes But is it not a heavy load?” she said said. “Yes, yes, too heavy,” he said; “but
that's not my fault; the foreman came just as we were starting, and would have
300 weight more put on to save him trouble, and I must get on with it as
well as I can.” He was raising the whip again, when
the lady said: “Pray, stop; I think I can help you if you will let me.” The man
laughed. “You see,” she said, “you do not give him a fair chance; he cannot use all his
power with his head held back as it is with that check crane if you would take
it off I'm sure he would do better— —do try it,” she said persuasively, “I should be
very glad if you would.” “Well, well,” said Jakes, with a short
laugh, “anything to please a lady, of course. How far would you wish it down,
ma'am?” “Quite down, give him his head alt together The rain was taken off, and in a
moment I put my heads down to my very knees. What a comfort it was! Then I
tossed it up and down several times to get the aching stiffness out of my
neck. “Poor fellow! that is what you wanted,” said she, patting and stroking me with
her gentle hand; “and now if you will speak kindly to him and lead him on I
believe he will be able to do better.” Jakes took the rain Come on,
Blackie.” I put down my head, and threw my whole weight against the collar; I spared
no strength; the load moved on, and I pulled it steady steadily up the hill,
and then stopped to take breath. The lady had walked along the
footpath, and now came across into the road. She stroked and patted my neck, as I
had not been patted for many a long day. “You see he was quite willing when
you gave him the chance I'm sure he is a fine tempered creature, and I dare say
has known better days. You won't put that rain on again, will you?” for he was just
going to hitch it up on the old plan well Well, ma'am, I can't deny that
having his head has helped him up the hill, and I'll remember it another time,
and thank you, ma'am; but if you went without a check reain I should be the
laughing stock of all the carters; it is a fashion, you
see.” “Is it not better,” she said, “to lead a
good fashion than to follow a bad one? A great many gentlemen do not use check
rains now; our carriage horses have not worn them for 15 years, and work with
much less fatigue than those who have them; besides,” she added in a very ser
ious voice, “we have no right to distress any of God's creatures without a very
good reason; we call them dumb animals, and so they are, for they cannot tell us
how they feel, but they do not suffer less because they have no
words. But I must not detain you now; I thank you for trying my plan with your
good horse, and I am sure you will find it far better than the whip good day and
with another soft pat on my neck she stepped lightly across the path, and I
saw her no more.
“That was a real lady, I'll be bound for it,” said Jakes to himself; “she spoke just
as polite as if I was a gentleman, and I'll try her plan, uphill, at any
rate;” and I must do him the justice to say that he let my rain out several
holes, and going uphill after that, he always gave me my head; but the heavy loads went
on. Good feed and fair rest will keep up one's strength under full work, but no
horse can stand against overloading; and I was getting so thoroughly pulled down
from this cause that a younger horse was brought in my
place. I may as well mention here what I suffered at this time from another cause.
I had heard horses speak of it, but had never myself had experience of the evil;
this was a badly lighted stable; there was only one very small window at the
end, and the consequence was that the stalls were almost
dark. Besides the depressing effect this had on my spirits, it very much weakened my sight,
and when I was suddenly brought out of the darkness into the glare of daylight
it was very painful to my eyes. Several times I stumbled over the threshold, and
could scarcely see where I was going. I believe, had I stayed there very
long, I should have become per blind and that would have been a great misfortune,
for I have heard men say that a stone Blind horse was safer to drive than one
which had imperfect sight, as it generally makes them very timid. However, I escaped without any
permanent injury to my sight, and was sold to a large cab owner end of chapter